Okay so today's דף daf is ע"ד ayin daled 74. We are
in the penultimate פרק perek here. Not penultimate, the ultimate פרק. perek.
We're in the last פרק, perek, finally talking moving beyond the עבודה
avoda and talking about the actual day of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
itself from our perspective focusing on the prohibitions. We'll get later into
the issues of the תפילה tefillah
and we kick off at the very top of ע"ד עמוד א.
ayin daled amud aleph. The issue here was the language of the
משנה mishna where the משנה mishna says that it was, what do
you call it, the משנה mishna says that it's אסור assur to
eat on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, אסור assur to eat and drink,
which the גמרא gemara sort of felt was a little bit of
an understatement given the prohibition of that it was biblical and that
it was a איסור כרת. issur kares. So the גמרא's gemara response
was that אסור assur can refer to the case of eating even
less than a שיעור shiur and it introduced the debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that less than the
minimum amount חצי שיעור chatzi shiur
is still going to be prohibited according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
biblically, according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish rabbinically. And that's the language
of אסור assur because it is forbidden, maybe even biblically or rabbinically,
but it's not, does not deserve the weight to say איסור כרת
issur kares because it's less than a שיעור. shiur. Within that debate,
and that's going to be the focus of our discussion today, is
that question of חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur. We have the question that
if somebody takes a שבועה shvua not to eat and they eat
טריפות treifus that according to the חכמים, chachamim, it's a debate of
the חכמים chachamim and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but according to the
חכמים chachamim they still transgress violating their שבועה. shvua. And the question
is why aren't they מושבע ועומד mushba ve'omed pre-sworn, fore-sworn against that
already? So one answer is it's called a כולל. kolel. He took
a general שבועה shvua not to eat, so although some of it
relates to things he's already fore-sworn against like טריפה, treifa, it also
relates to eating any food. So once it takes effect it takes
effect and therefore even if he eats טרף treif food the שבועה
shvua took effect and you violate not only eating טרף, treif, you
violate your שבועה. shvua. That's one answer. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said
no, the case was that he said a שבועה shvua that he
won't eat a half a שיעור. shiur. He won't eat less a
half a כזית. kezayis. According to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva you don't
even have to say that. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says a normal
שבועה shvua that says you won't eat means even a tiny amount.
So either you said it or you implied it and therefore you're
not מושבע ועומד. mushba ve'omed. You're not fore-sworn against a half a
כזית kezayis of חזיר chazir because that's not a biblical violation and
therefore your שבועה shvua takes effect. So the גמרא gemara says but
according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish if it's even minimally rabbinically forbidden
shouldn't you at least be fore-sworn, which is an interesting idea that
things that are rabbinic are also seen under a biblical mandate let's
say or prohibition of not to violate the words of the rabbis.
So how does that make sense? So let's pick up on the
גמרא's gemara answer. Two lines from the top on ע"ד עמוד א.
ayin daled amud aleph. One minute. וכי תימא Vechi teima
maybe you'll respond and say כיון דאית ליה היתר מן התורה keivan
de'is lei heter min hatorah since biblically it's permissible although the rabbis
forbade it קחיילא קרבן שבועה kachayla korban shvua that that's why the
שבועה shvua and the consequence of violating the שבועה, shvua, the קרבן
korban if you did it, if you did it unintentionally, maybe that's
why the prohibition of the שבועה shvua takes effect, that yes ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says it's rabbinically forbidden less than a שיעור shiur
but it's not biblical and so even though it is rabbinic the
שבועה shvua can take effect on
it. והתנן Vehatnan one minute. I'll give you an example where something
is only a rabbinic problem and the שבועה shvua does not take
effect, that just the rabbinic problem gets in the way of the
שבועה. shvua. שבועת העדות Shvuat ha'edut if you take a, now this
is basically what they would do before the age of subpoena, not
before the age but whatever. This is what the Torah sort of
mandates as how the, to use the, to have the same effect
as a subpoena is if you believe somebody has testimony for you
you take a שבועה shvua and you basically say, you know, you
impose a שבועה shvua on them that they don't, that if they
have any testimony they have to come and testify. And then if
the person you know withholds the testimony the Torah says אם לא
יגיד ונשא עונו im lo yagid venasa avono if they withhold the
testimony after they've been sworn to by you. It's outside of the
court.
You go and say I swear to you.
No, because there's actually, okay, we're not learning שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut
but actually it's a case where you can impose a שבועה shvua
on someone and therefore if they know testimony and withhold it they
will then violate. So who does that apply to? So when we
learn שבועות shvuot we can figure out all the parameters of that
but the משנה mishna says שבועת העדות אינה נוהגת אלא בראויין להעיד.
shvuat ha'edut einah noheget ela bir'uyin lehiahid. It only applies to people
who could come and give testimony now in the first place. Now
you'd say oh that's a reasonable statement. You know there are people
that are פסול. pasul. You have a, you know, גזלן, gazlan, you
have women who are not recognized you know according to הלכה halacha
in, you know, in a sort of an official way to give
testimony. Other ways in which women play, you know, can give evidence
but not in a formal role of עדות. eidut. And so on.
So that's who it's excluding. Only The problem is that the משנה
Mishnah had already said explicitly: it doesn't apply to women, it doesn't
apply to minors, it doesn't apply to גזלנים. gazlanim. So then it
says, and it only applies to people who can testify. So who
else are you excluding? Okay, ואבימנן בה, V'abimnan bah, and we asked
on this, למעוטי מאי, L'ma'utei mai, what is it additionally excluding? למעוטי
מאי? L'ma'utei mai? רב פפא Rav Papa אמר amar למעוטי מלך, L'ma'utei
melech,
a king. Because a king, you can't testify against him and he
can't testify in court for various reasons.
מלך לא דן ולא דנין.
Melech lo dan
v'lo danin. Right, but it's not mentioned in that משנה. Mishnah. So
that phrase, meaning we're not talking about mentioned elsewhere, that משנה Mishnah
did not explicitly exclude king, that's what it's excluding. רב אחא בר
יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov אומר omer למעוטי משחק בקוביא. L'ma'utei mesachek
b'kivya. No, to exclude people that are rabbinically
disqualified like a dice player, gamblers, right, gamblers are rabbinically disqualified. One
of two reasons: either because they're not involved in like ישובו של
עולם, Yishuvo shel olam,
the type of like, you know, labor that's productive labor, right, labor
that's helpful for the world. So therefore there's a concern that they're
at the margins there, you know, and
therefore they might be more easy to bribe and to pay off
for their testimony. And the other reason is a more technical reason.
It's that actually this is a type of גזילה, gezeila, it's maybe
rabbinic גזילה, gezeila, אסמכתא לא קניא, Asmachta lo kanya, but you make
a bet and you pay and the other person was really not
expecting to lose the bet, the only reason he made the bet.
So therefore there's like an element of גזילה gezeila going on here.
So those are various reasons. But either way, it's only rabbinic. And
here you imposed a biblical שבועה, shvuah, biblically this guy could come
up to the court. He's not testifying, he doesn't violate his שבועה.
shvuah. Because since rabbinically he can't, he's off the hook. So you
see the rabbinic prohibition has consequence in the world of שבועה. shvuah.
So why don't we say the same thing, that you're biblically forsworn
to, I mean the rabbinic prohibition of eating less than a שיעור
shiur prevents the biblical שבועה. shvuah. The same way here, the fact
that rabbinically you can't testify prevents the effect of this biblical שבועה.
shvuah. That's the question. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers.
והא משחק בקוביא מדאורייתא מיחזי חזי, V'ha mesachek b'kivya mide'oraisa mechzi chazi,
משחק בקוביא mesachek b'kivya is biblically allowed to testify. רבנן הוא דפסלוהו,
Rabbanan hu d'paslohu,
it's only the rabbis who invalidated him. And nevertheless, once the rabbis
invalidated him, the שבועה, shvuah, he's irrelevant, and the שבועה shvuah doesn't
take effect. So let's say the same about eating less than a
כזית. kezayis. ולא חלה שבועה עליה, V'lo chala shvuah alei,
and you see the שבועה shvuah doesn't take effect once he's rabbinically
prohibited. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם, Shani hatam, there
it's different. אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse says, אם לוא יגיד,
Im lo yagid, if he does not testify, ונשא עוונו, v'nasa avono,
he'll bear the burden of his sin. והאי לאו בר הגדה הוא
כלל, V'hai lav bar hagadah hu klal, he cannot testify. Meaning it
doesn't matter whether it's biblically he's qualified. The reality is, if he
shows up in court and says I'm here to testify, we'll slam
the door in his face. Even if he testifies, we'll dismiss the
testimony. So there's no way he can ever have any liability for
not testifying. The תורה Torah doesn't say if you're an עד, ed,
you bear the burden of your שבועה. shvuah. It says if you
don't testify. So we're only talking about somebody who practically has the
ability to testify. Okay, so let's say somebody is, I don't know,
is mute? Right, exactly. You know, let's say somebody is in prison
and it's impossible, nobody's going to let him out to testify. Oh,
but technically he's כשר לעדות. kasher l'edut. It doesn't matter. The שבועה
shvuah is for violating it, it's for when you had the ability
to testify and you didn't. Whatever's preventing you, whether it's the rabbinic
restriction or whether it's that you're locked up in jail, that you
cannot be held liable for violating the שבועה. shvuah. It's not about
being theoretically fit to testify. As opposed to our case. Our case
is even that you, are you considered to be forsworn? Are you
considered to have been biblically already prevented from eating this half of
a כזית kezayis of חזרת? chazeret? And the answer is no. You
might not be allowed to rabbinically, but it's not like you're מושבע,
mushba, like you're forsworn. The whole idea as we took a שבועה
shvuah on הר סיני. Har Sinai. You're not biblically forsworn. And that's
about the status of this half a כזית kezayis of חזרת. chazeret.
Is it something that already biblically is off limits? And there the
answer is no, and therefore your שבועה shvuah can take effect. Though,
yes.
I just don't remember what would the גמרא Gemara have had the
לשון lashon of the משנה Mishnah be if not
אסור?
assur? Oh, חייב כרת, chayav kares, כל האוכל ושותה, kol ha'ochel v'shoteh,
חייב כרת. chayav kares. Whatever.
You know, the implication that every time the משנה Mishnah says אסור
assur it
would have said חייב, chayav, it would have said חייב. chayav. Look.
Oh, you know, it's a fundamental issue, but the רמב"ם... Rambam... For
example in הלכות halakhot שבת Shabbat *Hilchos Shabbos* if I remember correctly
says that he says he's more even systematic than the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. He says every time I go to say אסור assur *asur*
it means דרבנן de'rabbanan *derabbanan*, every time I go to say חייב
*chayav* it means דאורייתא de'oraisa *de'oraisa*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not,
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is not as rigorous as that, but again
saying אסור assur *asur* which suggests דרבנן de'rabbanan *derabbanan* does not suggest
something weighty, minimally he should have said חייב *chayav*. כל kol האוכל
והשותה ביום הכיפורים חייב *kol ha'ochel vehashoseh b'Yom HaKippurim
chayav*, or maybe shorthand for חייב כרת chayav kares.
*chayav kares* or at least חייב *chayav* of a biblical לאו *lav*
or something more weighty.
אסור assur *asur* of all אסור assur *asur* דרבנן de'rabbanan, *derabbanan*, right?
Alright so that's the opposite, that's פטור אבל אסור assur *patur aval
asur* and anytime you say פטור *patur* means anyway. So okay so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* so that's the answer. Yes but according to
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish* it's rabbinic and that the fact
that it's not biblical by עדות *edus* is one thing, but here
the fact that it's not biblical is enough to say that the
שבועה Shevuah *shvuah* takes effect. By the way there's an interesting question
of פסולי עדות דרבנן derabbanan? *psulei edus derabbanan* for other הלכות Halachos
*halachos*. Let's say you have somebody in עדות *edus* at a wedding
or an עד *ed* of a גט *get* that's פסול דרבנן derabbanan
*pasul derabbanan*, right? Does that invalidate the wedding or the גט *get*?
Right? So there if the people that are עדים *edim* at the
wedding
or at גיטין *gittin* they're not coming to court to testify like
this case of שבועת העדות *shvuas ha'edus* where oh I can't the
court will never accept me, it's sort of just the need of
עדים *edim* to give weight to the act and to make the
act a meaningful act of קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin* or גירושין *geirushin*. So
do we say that it takes effect דאורייתא de'oraisa, *de'oraisa* or do
we say no the only reason the עדים *edim* give weight to
it is because in theory they could come to court and testify
and what would it apply to somebody who would never be accepted
in court? So there's a major debate of the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*
whether somebody who's פסול לעדות דרבנן derabbanan *pasul l'edus derabbanan* whether he
would invalidate a wedding or a גט דאורייתא de'oraisa, *get de'oraisa*.
So that's the only reason why a
woman can't be an עד *ed*? No, woman is פסול דאורייתא de'oraisa
*pasul de'oraisa*. So that's that's definitely. Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. וכל היכא דתני ענוש כרת kares. לא תני אסור
assur *vechol heicha detani enosh kares lo tani asur*. Now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* asks sort of Dov's question. One minute, what's getting you
so upset? You mean to tell me anytime you say something is
really weighty and punishable by כרת kares *kares* it wouldn't use the
phrase just forbidden? והתניא *vehasanya* we have a ברייתא braita *Braisah* that
says אף על פי שאמרו אסור assur, בכולן *af al pi she'amru
asur b'chulan* although they said that it's all forbidden which is basically
here exactly referring to our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *Yom Kippur*, it's אסור assur *asur* to eat to drink and
all these things and to bathe and anoint yourself even though it
says the phrase אסור *asur* by all of them לא אמרו ענוש
כרת kares, אלא אוכל ochel. ושותה ועושה מלאכה melacha. בלבד *lo amru
enosh kares ela ochel v'shoseh v'oseh melachah bilvad*. The only thing you
get כרת kares, *kares* for is eating and drinking and doing מלאכה
melacha, *melachah*. So you see the ברייתא Braisa *Braisah* very much clarifies
the word אסור *asur* in the משנה *Mishnah* refers to all of
them but the ברייתא braita *Braisah* clarifies that there's different weight to
אכילה ושתייה achila ushtiya, *achilah v'shtiyah* on the one hand and everything
else on the other. But you see אסור *asur* word אסור *asur*
could apply to all of them, it needs clarification but it could
apply. הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar* no this is what it means. כשאמרו
אסור *keshe'amru asur* when the ברייתא braita. *Braisah* is saying when the
משנה *Mishnah* says it's forbidden לא אמרו אלא בחצי שיעור shiur, *lo
amru ela b'chatzi shiur*. Number one is when it talks about eating
and drinking אסור *asur* only refers to a חצי שיעור Chatzi shiur.
*chatzi shiur*. Otherwise we wouldn't have used the phrase אסור *asur*. Okay?
אבל כשיעור *aval k'shiur* if we're talking about the full amount ענוש
כרת kares. *enosh kares* you get כרת karet. *kares*. So אף על
פי שענוש כרת karet *af al pi she'enosh kares* even though you
get כרת karet? *kares* ענוש כרת karet? אלא אוכל ושותה ועושה מלאכה
melacha. בלבד *enosh kares ela ochel v'shoseh v'oseh melachah bilvad*. You only
get it for eating and drinking and doing מלאכה melacha, *melachah*. Quite
a forced reread of that ברייתא Braisa *Braisah*. The ברייתא *Braisah* explicitly
acknowledges that the משנה *Mishnah* used the phrase אסור *asur* for everything
but points out the different weight. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is committed
to its idea that the word אסור *asur* would not be applied
to ענוש כרת karet *enosh kares* and therefore rereads the ברייתא *Braisah*
to say yes it uses אסור *asur* for all of these because
we're talking about חצי שיעור chatzi shiur. *chatzi shiur*. By the way
let me tell you amongst those things eating and drinking when you
do them כשיעור *k'shiur* you get כרת karet. *kares* but the other
things you'll never get כרת karet, *kares*. Okay? But again it's quite
bizarre because the whole point of the ברייתא *Braisah* is to point
out that although the same term is being used they're of different
weight and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rereads the ברייתא *Braisah* so that
it would not be the same term being used. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is very committed to the idea that it would not use
the word אסור *asur* by something that is ענוש כרת karet. *enosh
kares*. ואיבעית אימא *v'iba'is eima* and if you want says the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* כי תני אסור אשארא *ki tani asur asha'ara*. When it
says אסור *asur* right יום כיפור Yom Kippur אסור באכילה ושתייה *Yom
Kippur asur b'achilah v'shtiyah* it means yes I'm still committed to this
idea again somewhat ignoring the ברייתא *Braisah*, I'm still committed to this
idea that אסור *asur* will not refer to ענוש כרת karet, *enosh
kares* but rather than saying the משנה *Mishnah* is talking about a
חצי שיעור chatzi shiur, *chatzi shiur* we say אסור *asur* because that's
the appropriate term for the rest of the things in the משנה
*Mishnah*. Another way to offset it is since we're going to mention
like רחיצה *rechitza* סיכה *sicha* נעילת הסנדל *ne'ilas hasandal* תשמיש המיטה *tashmish
hamitah* and for those the right word to use is אסור *asur*
so we throw in אכילה ושתייה achila v'shtiya *achilah v'shtiyah* as well.
If we were just talking about אכילה achilah. ושתייה *achilah v'shtiyah* we
wouldn't say אסור *asur* we'd say חייב *chayav* but since אסור *asur*
applies to the rest of the list that's the word we're going
to use in the משנה *Mishnah*. And that's a very reasonable explanation
and that explains the ברייתא. So the ברייתא comes along and says
yes, we'll use the word אסור for all of them, but you
should be aware that the first two are in a very different
category. Okay, so yes, in principle אסור would never have applied to
the first two, we used it because it applies to the rest
of the list, and even though we've used the word אסור for
the whole list, be aware that the first two are of a
very different type and are עונש כרת. onesh kares. What's the עונש?
onesh? So we'll talk about that in a minute. Okay. Okay, דתנו
רבה ורב יוסף, detanu Rabba ve-Rav Yosef, because Rabba and Rav Yosef
taught, בשאר ספרי דבי רב, bishe'ar Sifrei d'vei Rav, in the other
books of the House of Rav, I'm going to get back to
explain what that means in a minute, דתנו, detanu, מניין ליום הכיפורים
שאסור ברחיצה וסיכה ונעילת הסנדל ובתשמיש המיטה? minyin l'Yom HaKippurim she-assur birchitza
v'sicha v'ne'ilat hasandal u-vetashmish hamita? How do you know Yom Kippur is
forbidden in bathing, anointing, wearing sandals, and sex? התלמוד לומר שבתון. ha-talmud
lomar Shabbaton. It says it shall be, you know, it's a שבתון
שבות, Shabbaton shevut, it shall be a day of cessation, cessation of
even of these related issues that relate to afflicting yourself, even these
other issues. So now there's a lot to unpack here. Number one
is what is this שאר ספרי דבי רב, she'ar Sifrei d'vei Rav,
the other books of the House of Rav? If you take a
look at רש״י, Rashi, five lines before the lines get wide, רש״י
Rashi says שאר ספרי, she'ar Sifrei, דלאו תורת כהנים, d'lav Torat Kohanim,
all the other Tannaitic sort of books that are not תורת כהנים.
Torat Kohanim. ספר וידבר, Sefer Vayidaber, meaning במדבר, Bamidbar, ואלה הדברים, v'Eileh
HaDevarim, which is: what is the name of the מדרש הלכה Midrash
Halacha on במדבר Bamidbar and דברים? Devarim? Anybody? ספרי, Sifrei, which means
books. If you think about it, what's the work on ויקרא Vayikra
called? ספרא. Sifra. Some call it תורת כהנים, Torat Kohanim, but ספרא.
Sifra. So it's like 'the' book. Exactly. Because תורת כהנים Torat Kohanim
is, you know, there's probably the most elaboration, it's actually quite fascinating
why that's true. There's a, an article out by Shlomo Naeh from
about 20 years ago or so, where he actually wants to argue
that the Tannaitic work on ויקרא, Vayikra, the ספרא, Sifra, תורת כהנים,
Torat Kohanim, is the earliest work of תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al
peh that was ever written down. Which, and he makes it quite
early, which is fascinating, because even the גמרא Gemara wasn't, you know,
the משנה wasn't written down until like the fifth, sixth century or
whatever. He argues that the תורת כהנים Torat Kohanim was written down
already in the Tannaitic period. He thinks that it's because, as we
know, as we've been talking about all along, the shift from a
Temple-oriented, you know, focused religion to a תורה Torah one, that there
was, you know, for so long it was all about the Temple,
that the earliest stuff that was written down and the initial focus
of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah was around הלכות related to the מקדש.
Mikdash. Anyway, so תורת כהנים, Torat Kohanim, which fascinating how he proves
it, I just have to tell you how he proves it because
the article starts out like it's going to be the most boring
article on the planet, because he talks about different organizations of the
ספרא. Sifra. If you've ever tried to find something in the ספרא,
Sifra, it's impossible. It's divided up into פרשיות parshiyot and פרקים, perakim,
and there's like three different systems of organization going on there. So
he looks at all of the different systems of organization, makes all
these charts, tries to figure out like what the original organization is,
like it's you know, so crazy technical. But the upshot is he
finds out that the original organization is not based on, you know,
theme, is not based on פרשה, parsha, it's based on length. Length.
It has a standard length, right? And he says: why do you
want a standard length? Other things in the Rabbinic literature aren't divided
up by length. You have פרקים perakim that are huge, the first
פרק perek of קידושין, פרקים perakim that are tiny. He says: what
things do you need standard length for? Scrolls. Remember, remember when we
used to have things called cassette tapes? Remember how cassette tapes were
60 to 90 minutes, maybe at the most 120? Because you don't
want it too short, then you need a million cassette tapes. You
don't want it too long, then you need too much scrolling to
do. So when things are scrolls, you need them to be within
a standard size, and he shows how in the classical world, there
was a standard size for scrolls, which corresponds to the division of
תורת כהנים. Torat Kohanim. And that's his argument that תורת כהנים Torat
Kohanim actually was the first written work of תורה שבעל פה. Torah
she-be'al peh. Fascinating article. Anyway, I say all this because I want
another digression, but because תורת כהנים Torat Kohanim is 'the' ספר. sefer.
It's like the primary work of מדרש הלכה. Midrash Halacha. And then
the other מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha on the other works of the
תורה, Torah, במדבר Bamidbar and דברים, Devarim, is the ספרי, Sifrei, the
other books, the other books. שאר ספרי דבי רב. she'ar Sifrei d'vei
Rav. Sometimes you'll see on an edition of the ספרי, Sifrei, it'll
be ספרי דבי רב, Sifrei d'vei Rav, the House of Rav, because
רב, Rav, as a very early אמורא, Amora, was seen as like
the editor of the ספרי. Sifrei. By the way, while we're talking
about it, what's the name of the work on the מדרש הלכה
Midrash Halacha on שמות? Shemot? מכילתא. Mekhilta. You know what מכילתא Mekhilta
means? Collection. Collection, right? So very generic word. The book, the books,
collection. Anyway, fine. So they taught this in the ספרי, Sifrei, which
is quite fascinating because of the פסוק pasuk they quoted from ויקרא,
Vayikra, שבתון שבות, Shabbaton shevut, so I don't know which פסוק pasuk
it was going on. That's number one, the phrase of שאר ספרי
דבי רב. she'ar Sifrei d'vei Rav. Number two, this is now fascinating
because now we have the basis for the prohibition of these other
things, of the things that are not eating and drinking. So let's
take a look at where this prohibition comes from. Look at the
רש"י Rashi now, the next רש"י, Rashi, four lines from the wide
lines, שבתון. Shabbaton. גבי עינוי כתיב, Gabei Inui Ksiv, it says by
עינוי, Inui, right? What does it say at the end, right? We
just finished reading through the whole עבודה Avoda in אחרי מות. Achrei
Mos. What does it say after the עבודה Avoda of אחרי מות?
Achrei Mos? It says after the whole עבודה, Avoda, the עבודה Avoda
of אחרי מות, Achrei Mos, it says כי ביום הזה יכפר עליכם
לטהר אתכם מכל חטאתיכם לפני ה׳ תטהרו שבת שבתון היא לכם ועניתם
את נפשתיכם חקת עולם. Ki bayom hazeh yechaper aleichem letaher etchem mikol
chatoteichem lifnei Hashem titharu Shabbat Shabbaton hi lachem ve'initem et nafshoteichem chukat
olam. So שבתון Shabbaton is connected to עינוי. Inui. So what does
that mean? גבי עינוי כתיב, Gabei Inui Ksiv, דהיכי דשבתון האמור בשבת
אסמכו ביה רבנן שאר מלאכות שלא היו במשכן ואינם מלאכה גמורה. d'heichi
d'Shabbaton ha'amur b'Shabbat asmechu bei Rabbanan shear melachot shelo hayu b'mishkan ve'einam
melacha gmura. The same way the word שבתון Shabbaton is something by
שבת Shabbat that the Rabbis used to connect to it other things
that are—quite fascinating phrase of רש"י—other Rashi מלאכות melachot that are not
real מלאכה. melacha We would have said rabbinic restrictions, but fascinating that
רש"י Rashi calls the rabbinic restrictions on שבת Shabbat other מלאכות melachot
of a lesser nature. שלא היו במשכן, Shelo hayu b'mishkan, they're not
the real מלאכה, melacha, but he calls them מלאכה. melacha, But the
same way שבתון Shabbaton is a concept by שבת Shabbat, to create
the whole rabbinic prohibitions of שבת, Shabbat הכא נמי hacha nami here
too, שבתון Shabbaton גבי עינוי gabei Inui דכתיב de'ksiv שבת שבתון היא
לכם ועניתם, Shabbat Shabbaton hu lachem ve'initem, להוסיף על עינוי אכילה ושתייה
דאתייא—it's lehosif al Inui achila ushtiya de'atya coming to add to the
sense of affliction—אכילה achilah. ושתייה, the primary affliction and to add to
it these other things of washing and bathing. Now, that is a
very ambiguous רש"י Rashi because if I asked you according to רש"י,
Rashi, is are these other things biblical or rabbinic, what would you
say? Rabbinic. You start by saying rabbinic because he says אסמכו ביה
רבנן, asmechu bei Rabbanan, the Rabbis. But then first of all, the
term he uses שאר מלאכות shear melachot by שבת Shabbat, is suggestive,
but also when he says this phrase להוסיף על עינוי אכילה ושתייה,
lehosif al Inui achila ushtiya, it's coming the פסוק, Pasuk, the phrase
is coming להוסיף. lehosif. He doesn't say because of this phrase the
Rabbis used it as an אסמכתא asmachta and added. The phrase is
coming להוסיף. lehosif. So this is going to get us into these
fascinating debates of the ראשונים Rishonim whether the other עינויים Inuyim are
biblical or rabbinic. Is it rabbinic and this is an אסמכתא? asmachta?
Is it biblical but maybe a little open-ended biblical? Like the exact
parameters of what's included in this idea of שבתון, Shabbaton, that's for
the Rabbis to figure out, to define, but the concept and the
basic idea is a biblical one. There are ראשונים Rishonim that believe
that the extra עינויים Inuyim are biblical but the Rabbis have somewhat
of a free hand of defining its character and shape. I think
רש"י Rashi is quite ambiguous on that score. He starts by saying
אסמכו רבנן, asmechu Rabbanan, he ends by saying that it is the
פסוק Pasuk is coming להוסיף. lehosif. So that's one question of biblical-rabbinic.
There's another important question, which is what are the nature of these
additional עינויים Inuyim or the nature of עינוי Inui at all? First
of all, by שבתון Shabbaton by שבת, Shabbat? what is the nature
of the rabbinic restrictions on שבת? Shabbat So there's actually both רמב"ם
Rambam and רמב"ן Ramban say that the rabbinic restrictions derived from the
biblical concept of שבתון. Shabbaton. And by the way, there too they
make it clear that it's not just דרבנן and an אסמכתא. asmachta.
They see that the process of rabbinic legislation on שבת Shabbat. of
דרבנן is giving like meat and bones to a biblical mandate of
שבתון Shabbaton that goes beyond the מלאכות. melachot. That it's connecting ultimately
to a biblical idea of שבתון Shabbaton and it's not just an
אסמכתא. asmachta. What is the concept of that rabbinic שבתון? Shabbaton? Here
there's an interesting debate. The רמב"ן Ramban says the primary concept, not
of all דרבנן, but of the idea of שבתון Shabbaton in the
תורה Torah in addition to מלאכה, melacha. is that it's not just
about creative activity, but it's about exerting labor—labor exertions. It's about work
that we would call work—exertion. And that he says is the concept
of שבתון Shabbaton in the תורה. Torah. רמב"ם Rambam says no, שבתון
Shabbaton in the תורה, Torah, and this connects to רש"י's Rashi idea
of שאר מלאכות, shear melachot, tells the Rabbis that what has to
be forbidden is not just the מלאכה melacha proper, but anything that
could lead to the מלאכה, melacha. like reading by candlelight, or anything
that's similar to a מלאכה, melacha for example, like doing a something
with a שינוי. shinui. Okay,
so technically you're off the hook, but it still... right, exactly, something
that looks like cooking. So for the רמב"ם, Rambam, the שבתון Shabbaton
means things that are similar to the core מלאכות melachot as opposed
to רמב"ן Ramban where they are a separate but related concept, it's
not just about creative activity, it's about exertion. That's by שבת. Shabbos.
By יום כיפור Yom Kippur as well, there's an interesting question of
how do you understand the basic idea of עינוי Inui and to
what degree is עינוי Inui connected to the idea of שבתון? Shabbaton?
Mostly we think, what's the idea of עינוי? Inui? Starvation. some type
of a תשובה Teshuvah process, you know exactly you make yourself pained
and you know and you're doing these things and it should be
a כפרה Kapparah etcetera. רמב״ם Rambam calls his הלכות of יום כיפורים,
Yom Kippurim, הלכות שביתת עשור, Hilchos Shevisas Asor, the resting on the
tenth day. And he says the תורה Torah says שבתון, Shabbaton, שבת
שבתון היא לכם, Shabbos Shabbaton hee lachem, שבת ממלאכה, Shabbos mimelacha, שבת
מאכילה ושתייה. Shabbos meachila u'shtiya. That it's actually an idea of separating
from the world. The same way we normally separate from the world
in terms of doing labor, we're going to separate from the physical
aspects of the world and not engage in the physicality of the
world and we're going to spend one day at this very elevated
plane of not act of trying to be you know as non-physical
as possible. But it's not about hurting yourself. It's about freeing yourself
from this you know anchoring in the physical world. Very different type
of a concept. So it's worth noting that this דרשה Derasha of
the other of the other עינויים inuyim focuses on the word of
שבתון Shabbaton and the parallel that רש״י Rashi is giving us to
the way the idea of שבתון Shabbaton by שבת. Shabbos, So a
couple again to review a very interesting point that we number one.
Number one interesting question of the מדרשי הלכה, Midreshei Halacha, שאר ספרי
דבי רב, Sha'ar Sifrei d'vei Rav, the idea I went off on
a little tangent about the ספרי Sifrei but the important idea is
the ספרא Sifrah of תורת כהנים Toras Kohanim as opposed to the
other ones. Number two, the idea of of is the are the
עינויים inuyim of יום כיפור Yom Kippur דאורייתא de'oraisa, דרבנן? רש״י Rashi
sort of I think is a little ambivalent about that, speaks about
דרבנן then says the פסוק Pasuk is coming to add. And number
three the parallel to שבת, Shabbos which is that by שבת Shabbat
you also have an idea of שבתון. Shabbaton. רמב״ם Rambam and רמב״ן
Ramban also think it's a דאורייתא, de'oraita. although the דרבננז derabbanans came
to give sort of like I said you know the form to
it and shape to it and so on. There there's a debate
how you can conceptualize what that concept of שבתון Shabbaton is. How
does it relate to the מלאכות? Melachos? רש״י Rashi emphasizes a very
close connection to the מלאכות. Melachos. And by יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
as well, do we conceptualize the issue of עינוי inuy from a
שבתון Shabbaton concept or do we conceptualize it in a very different
way? Affliction, pain, suffering, תשובה Teshuvah and so on, or is it
more related to
this שבת שבתון Shabbos Shabbaton concept? Yes? And you conclude that שאר
עינויים She'ar Inuyim are biblical but with a lesser עונש? onesh?
That certainly, they're not כרת. kares, That we've been saying. The question
is saying more than just not כרת kares. because we'll see there
are exceptions to the rule and so on. So that's why most
ראשונים Rishonim that say it's דאורייתא, de'oraita. everybody says it's not כרת,
kares, that was the whole point. Most ראשונים though that say it's
דאורייתא say about clear דעשה d'asei but the rabbis have a pretty
free hand in defining what is
the content of that שבתון. Shabbaton. Okay? Does the רמב״ן Ramban argue
that something like שבות Shvus and and מוקצה Muktzeh are about exertion?
No, he says he admits that there's plenty of דרבננז derabbanans that
are not about שבתון. Shabbaton. But those דרבננז derabbanans that are linked
to the שבתון Shabbaton concept are the ones that are about exertion,
is his primary point. There's also one that would be like also
also like a day of business and so on, other things.
Money? Yeah, exactly. So what does the רמב״ן Ramban do with the
לשון lashon of עינוי? inuy? It's fine to say
from שבתון Shabbaton and it's really withdrawal from the but Okay, that's
a good question. Let's keep that in mind as we're going through.
Okay, so anyway where did we end right now? We have a
most satisfying answer where the גמרא Gemara concedes look, it doesn't want
to give out the
idea that אסור fundamentally would never apply to חיוב כרת chiyuv kares
but it concedes that we use the word אסור because of the
rest of the things on the list. And once there we're going
to use the word אסור and there it's not כרת, kares, it's
a דאורייתא, דרבנן we know it's not כרת. kares. We use the
word אסור, everything in the ברייתא comes to clarify, yes we use
the word אסור but don't forget אכילה achilah. ושתייה is חייב כרת.
Now we go to the looking at the issue of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish We'll get back to יום
כיפור Yom Kippur in a little bit. גופא. Gufa. Let's go back
to that earlier issue. חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
אמר amar אסור מן התורה. assur min HaTorah. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says it's biblical by eating less of a שיעור, shiur presumably by
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur we said it by other forbidden foods. The
whole discussion by the שבועה and a half of a half of
a כזית kezayis of of like חזיר. chazir. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
אמר amar מותר מן התורה. mutar min HaTorah. It's biblically permissible. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר amar אסור מן התורה. assur min HaTorah. It's
biblically forbidden. Why? כיון דחזי לאצטרופי, Keivan d'chazi l'itztarufei,
since in theory it could combine with with you know you could
eat a half כזית kezayis and another half כזית, kezayis, איסורא קא
אכיל, issura ka achil, you're eating something forbidden. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
אמר amar מותר מן התורה. mutar min HaTorah. It's biblically permissible. Why?
אכילה אמר רחמנא, Achila amar Rachmana, the תורה Torah normally says don't
eat, דליכא, d'leka, you didn't do an act of eating. Now it's
quite fascinating that they're debating it conceptually. In a minute we're going
to see that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan bases himself on a verse.
And this question of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan by well it's חזי
לאצטרופי, chazi l'itztarufei, you know what does that mean? Like you know
there's actually some אחרונים Acharonim just to tell you who say let's
say you ate a half
of a כותבת koseves on יום כיפור Yom Kippur right as the
sun was setting or right as the stars were coming out. So
it's not חזי לאצטרופי, chazi l'itztarufei, there's no way it's the beginning
of a process, you'll never be able on this יום כיפור Yom
Kippur this will never have turned into right a forbidden act. What
would ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say? So part of this is a
question of what does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish mean by... חזי לאיצטרופי,
chazi l'itstrufei, what's the point of it? And we actually should take
a step back and say why is it that there normally is
a minimum, why is there a minimum that you don't get lashes
for חזיר chazir unless you eat a כזית? kezayit? How do you
conceptualize that? So there's actually a two basic ways of understanding this.
This is like in classic בריסקער למדות. Brisker lomdus. One is, did
you eat חזיר? chazir? Yeah, you ate חזיר. chazir. But you know
what? If you didn't do it, if you, you know, there's a
minimum threshold that it was bad enough to be to get some
punishment for. But if I said, but if the תורה Torah says
don't eat חזיר, chazir, ולא תאכל כל נבילה, v'lo tochal kol neveilah,
did I transgress that verse? Did I eat נבילה? neveilah? Yes, you
did. But you just didn't do enough of it that you're deserving
of punishment. Technically, that's really saying you transgressed the law, it's just
a minimum for the threshold to be punished for. If that's the
way you conceptualize it, right, then that's חצי שיעור אסור מן התורה.
chatzi shiur asur min haTorah. Then when the תורה Torah says don't
do it, even a tiny bit you've transgressed. The שיעור shiur. is
just said for a minimum to get lashes, but you've already transgressed.
That's a total רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan read of it. Okay, there's
another way to say it. The another way of saying it is,
it's not that you did the act. To consider an act, not
just you've got enough eating. To say that you ate, you don't
eat until you've eaten a כזית. kezayit. Otherwise, what you'd say, I
tasted the חזיר, chazir, I nibbled on the חזיר. chazir. You wouldn't
say I ate. There's a minimum amount that qualitatively changes the nature
of the act and says you ate. So that's what ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish is saying. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. is saying you didn't
do an act of eating חזיר. chazir. Did חזיר chazir go in
your body? Yeah, but could we say you did an act of
eating? You didn't do an act of eating. רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's
response could be you did an act but you just don't get
the punishment, but that doesn't seem like that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's
response. His response seems to be, I'm not debating that you didn't
do an act of eating. But was the thing that you put
in your body, was it called חזיר? chazir? Yes, it was called
חזיר. chazir. So even if all you did was nibble חזיר, chazir,
you didn't eat חזיר, chazir, you tasted חזיר, chazir, you nibbled it,
right, that also the תורה Torah would forbid. It's not the same
prohibition, it's not לא תאכל, lo tochal, you know, לא תאכלו lo
tochlu or whatever, but once the תורה Torah says לא תאכלו, lo
tochlu, the תורה Torah implicitly is saying don't nibble it, don't taste
it, don't do other things about getting it in your body either.
That's like an implicit sub-thing. It's not the act of אכילה. achilah,
And that's why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, since it's חזי לאיצטרופי,
chazi l'itstrufei, notice the phrase in the גמרא, איסורא קאכיל. isura ka-achiyo.
He didn't say because it's חזי לאיצטרופי chazi l'itstrufei you did an
act of eating. I'm not debating it. Until you eat a כזית,
kezayit, you didn't, what you did, the act is not considered אכילה.
achila, But what I am saying is, that since if I nibble
a little bit and five minutes later I nibble a little bit
more, we combine them, that shows me that at least in terms
of how we're relating to the object, we're still considering it חזיר,
chazir, right, you've still put חזיר chazir in your body. If you
put חזיר chazir in your body, you've still done something wrong. Okay,
so that is רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's position is. So it's a
nice interesting conceptual debate. Maybe A, you could say you've done eating
but you don't get מלקות malkut but you still transgress. That would
be a very strong version of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Maybe everybody
could agree the act you did is not called an act of
אכילה. achila, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says even if you didn't do
an act of אכילה, you put חזיר chazir in your body, you've
done something wrong. Which, and let's take a look now as the
גמרא tries to base it on a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so the
גמרא says like this, איתיבי, eitivei, I think there's some hands but
I want to just for, get, get a little bit further here.
איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. Eitivei Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan challenged ריש לקיש. אין לי אלא כל שישנו בעונש ישנו
באזהרה. Ein li ela kol she-yeshno b'onesh yeshno b'azharah. I only know,
this is by the פסוקים pesukim of not eating חלב. chelev. It
says, it says כל חלב לא תאכלו, kol chelev lo tochlu, don't
eat any חלב, chelev, כי כל אוכל חלב ונכרתה, ki kol ochel
chelev v'nichretah, anybody who eats חלב chelev will get כרת. So I
only know people that will get כרת are the people that transgress.
How about somebody who won't get כרת? Is it possible to transgress
without getting כרת? כוי, koy, which is this animal that's a hybrid
between a בהמה behemah and a חיה, chayah, וחצי שיעור, v'chatzi shiur,
if you ate less than the שיעור. shiur הואיל ואינו בעונש, ho-il
v'eino b'onesh, maybe because you don't get the prohibition. כוי koy because
we don't, it's indeterminate if it's a חיה chayah or בהמה, behemah,
you won't get כרת for
only the חלב chelev of the בהמה behemah is forbidden. And a
half a שיעור shiur you don't get כרת. יכול אינו באזהרה, Yachol
eino b'azharah,
perhaps those are not prohibited. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, כל חלב. kol
chelev.
It says don't eat any חלב. chelev. So yes, when it says
you get כרת, it says כי כל אוכל חלב, ki kol ochel
chelev, but as רש״י Rashi points out the word כל kol there
is modifying the word אוכל. כל אוכל. kol ochel. Okay, but only
when you eat real חלב chelev do you get כרת. However, for
the prohibition, כל חלב לא תאכלו, kol chelev lo tochlu, even sort
of quasi-חלב chelev you get כרת, excuse me, is prohibited. And what
is that? כוי koy and חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says you see look, חצי שיעור, chatzi shiur it's still
prohibited. We learn it from the verse of כל חלב. kol chelev.
Says the גמרא says no, תלמוד לומר מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא. Talmud
lomar mi-drabbanan v'kra asmachata b'alma. It's only rabbinic, the verse is just
you know rabbinic a hinge for the rabbis to hang their hat
on, you know it's a peg, but really it's all rabbinic. It's
not מדאורייתא mi-d'Oraita from כל חלב. kol chelev. By the way, that
makes sense. אי סלקא דעתך דאורייתא, Ee salka da'atach de'oraita, if it's
biblical, this פסוק, pasuk, if we're serious that כל חלב Kol Helev
prohibits half of a כזית kezayit and the חלב helev of a
כוי. koy. So כוי ספקא הוא. Koy sfeika hu. So כוי, koy,
we don't know whether it's a חיה chaya or בהמה. behema. איצטריך
קרא לאתויי ספקא? Itzterich kra le'atuyei sfeika? Why would the verse tell
us, oh, by the way, it's still prohibited to eat a כוי,
koy, right? Of course it's prohibited, meaning God knows if it's חיה
chaya or בהמה, behema, so God has already told us whether, you
know, whether we can or can't eat it. And if we don't
know, we'll take the logical step of playing it safe. Why would
the פסוק pasuk come and tell us this thing that you don't
know, by the way, it's still prohibited? I mean, that's our ignorance.
So the גמרא says no, אי משום הא לא איריא, Ee mishum
ha lo irya, that wouldn't prove it, that which is rabbinic. קסבר,
Kasavar, because maybe the author of this ברייתא holds כוי בריה בפני
עצמה היא, Koy birya bifnei atzma hi,
that a כוי koy is not a חיה, chaya, not a בהמה,
behema, it's in a middle category. And therefore, that's a good question.
The תורה Torah says don't eat the חלב helev of a בהמה.
behema. You can eat the חלב helev of a חיה. chaya. What
about something that is neither בהמה behema nor חיה? chaya? It's right
in the middle of those two, a כוי. koy. Is that prohibited
or not? In a way, that's like a qualitative חצי שיעור, chatzi
shiur right? It's like a quasi חלב בהמה, helev behema, but it's
a quasi בהמה. behema. So that also is prohibited based on כל
חלב. Kol Helev. Okay, so that's how come this פסוק pasuk very
well could be דאורייתא. Okay, ואי לא תימא הכי, Ve'ee lo teima
hachi, if you don't say that, הא דאמר רב אידי בר אבין,
Ha de'amar Rav Idi bar Avin, אף כל לאתויי כוי. Af kol
le'atuyei koy. So when we say כל דם לא תאכלו, Kol dam
lo tochelu, right, don't eat any blood, so the גמרא says, what's
the word כל come to do? It's coming to include the blood
of a כוי. koy. So גמרא says, why would you need that?
כוי ספקא הוא, Koy sfeika hu, איצטריך קרא לרבויי ספקא? Itzterich kra
leribuyei sfeika? So again, same question, why did you need to include
the blood of a כוי? koy? אלא בריה שאני. Ela birya shani.
Yeah, because it's its own category, maybe although there it's even more
bizarre, the תורה Torah prohibits both the blood of a חיה chaya
and a בהמה. behema. Nevertheless, maybe because a כוי koy is in
its own category, its blood would be
permissible. הכא נמי בריה שאני. Hacha nami birya shani. So here too,
yes, כל חלב Kol Helev could be needed biblically if כוי koy
is its own category, needed biblically, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would
argue that yes, from כל חלב Kol Helev we learn the biblical
prohibition of חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur So now a minute, רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan's argument is not just
conceptual, look, you're putting חלב helev in your body, you're putting חזיר
chazir in your body, even if you didn't do an אכילה, that's
the תורה Torah also would prohibit that. He's got a פסוק pasuk
to base it on, כל חלב. Kol Helev. So that tells you
even when you don't do the act itself, any type of ingestion
of this thing
would also be forbidden. Now,
it's an interesting, two interesting questions I just have to say about
חצי שיעור chatzi shiur that emerge from here. Number one is, would
it apply to anything that is not about food? Let's say, for
example, I carry on שבת Shabbat half the minimum amount, I cook
on שבת Shabbat half the minimum amount. According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, have I biblically violated שבת Shabbat, or not? There's actually an
interesting debate, a number of פוסקים poskim say no, it only applies
to food. Why does it only apply to food? Because at the
end of the day it comes from a פסוק pasuk of כל
חלב. Kol Helev. כל חלב לא תאכלו. Kol helev lo tochelu. So
we can broaden that conceptually and say that's referring to all מאכלות
אסורות, ma'achalot assurot, all forbidden foods, right? Or all eating, יום כיפור
Yom Kippur is like a forbidden food but all eating. But we
have no basis of broadening that verse to things that are not
about food, at least not biblically. So it wouldn't be biblical. By
the way, for the Michaels in the room, we פוסקן pasken like
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and it is, חצי שיעור Chatzi shiur is
דאורייתא. But not according to many פוסקים poskim would say by non-foods
because it's based on this verse. Okay, another way of explaining why
it might not apply to non-foods is the point I've been making.
If you deal with a forbidden object, so right, remember רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan's phrase is איסורא קא אכיל, issura ka achil, it's still
חזיר chazir you're putting in your mouth. If you deal with a
forbidden object, right, so you can say objectively even though you haven't
done an אכילה, you've done something wrong, you've ingested this forbidden thing.
It's in your body, right? So that's something that's intrinsically problematic. When
things relate not to the object but to the act, don't do
an act of cooking, so then you could say did I start
the process? Yes. But I haven't, it's not like I did the
act of cooking and it's not like there was an object that
was problematic, that was taboo. Right? The whole idea of מאכלות אסורות
ma'achalot assurot is a concept like this is a taboo thing, so
keep off-limits. So any type of engagement with it could be problematic.
So that's why some say it only applies to foods, others disagree.
One other interesting question about חצי שיעור Chatzi shiur is, is it
a generic prohibition like learned from כל חלב Kol Helev is translated
as a prohibition
don't eat any חצי שיעור Chatzi shiur of any forbidden foods, or
is it a sub-category of the prohibition that it refers to? חצי
שיעור chatzi shiur of דם dam is like a quasi violation of
דם. dam. חצי שיעור chatzi shiur. of חמץ, chametz, a quasi violation
of חמץ. chametz. חצי שיעור chatzi shiur of חזיר, chazir, quasi violation
of חזיר. chazir. What difference does it make? So the רמב"ן Ramban
already asks the following question, he says... The הלכה halacha is if
somebody's life is in danger, then you you can violate prohibitions in
order to save their life, but you violate the lesser prohibition first,
okay? Because rather than the higher prohibition. He says let's say to
save this guy's life, you can feed him either a half of
a כזית kezayit of דם, dam, which is an איסור כרת, issur
kares, or a half of a כזית kezayit of חזיר, chazir, okay?
Would there be a preference to give him the חזיר chazir before
the דם? dam? Are they both a generic prohibition of חצי שיעור
and they're both the same weight? Or do we say, no, one
is a quasi דם dam prohibition, the other's a quasi חזיר. chazir.
Quasi דם dam is worse than quasi חזיר chazir because דם dam
is כרת, okay? So very interesting debate around how to conceptualize these
issues. I have a feeling I just lost everyone. No, you got
it.
Just as we perceived eating on יום כיפור Yom Kippur as the
ענויים, inuim, it should make a difference.
Well, that is interesting and this is the last thing I'm going
to say. A lot of this makes sense when you focus on
forbidden foods, which is like I said, like what we call an
איסור חפצא, issur cheftza, like the object is taboo and problematic. The
logic to apply it to יום כיפור Yom Kippur is not so
obvious, because by יום כיפור Yom Kippur? it really is about the
state of being satiated or unsatiated or the act of eating. It's
not really about the object being problematic, so it actually is a
little—it's hard within this approach to sort of just throw יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. into the same category. Okay, let's continue in the גמרא.
Now we actually—that's the end of חצי שיעור. I just gave you
like a whole שיעור on חצי שיעור in five minutes, so he's
unpacking. But anyway, it's a חצי שיעור שיעור. chatzi shiur shiur. But
okay, now we get to the other theme we introduced of where
we know that you're not—you know, the additional ענויים. inuim. But even
before the additional ענויים, inuim, where do you know you're not allowed
to eat and drink on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur The פסוק pasuk
just says תענו, teanu, afflict yourself. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן:
tanu rabbanan: תענו את נפשותיכם, teanu et nafshoteichem, so you should afflict
yourself. יכול ישב בחמה ובצינה, yakhol yeshev bechama uvetzina, maybe it means
like sit in the sun or sit in the cold, other ways
of afflicting your body. כדי שיצטער, kedai sheyitztaer, like you should be
in pain. תלמוד לומר: וכל מלאכה לא תעשו. talmud lomar vechol melacha
lo taasu. It links "do not do" or juxtaposes עינוי inui with
not doing מלאכה. melacha מה מלאכה שב ואל תעשה, ma melacha shev
veal taaseh, the same way the way you refrain from מלאכה melacha
is by not doing something, it's basically as in don't do X,
don't do מלאכה. melacha אף עינוי נפש שב ואל תעשה. af inui
nefesh shev veal taaseh. So also afflicting yourself means don't do something.
You can't be—it's as opposed to saying go go to the sun,
it won't be saying go sit in the sun. It would be—if
you're in the sun—so right, ואימא היכא דיתיב בשמשא וחמים ליה לא
נימא ליה קום תוב בטולא, ve'eima heicha deyativ beshimsha vechamim lei lo
neima lei kum tuv betula, maybe it can be saying pass—don't do
something, don't get out of the sun. If you're in the sun
and it's difficult for you, don't get out of it. יתיב בטולא
וקריר ליה לא נימא ליה קום תוב בשמשא, yativ betula vekarir lei
lo neima lei kum tuv beshimsha, you're in the shade and it's
cold for you, we won't tell you to sit in the sun,
but we'll tell you don't, you know, we won't tell you to
sit in the sun, but we'll tell you don't go sit in
the sun. So maybe here too you could passively do עינוי inui
by staying where you are. So the גמרא says no, דומיא דמלאכה,
dumya demelacha, it's similar to מלאכה melacha in the following way. מה
מלאכה לא חילקת בה, ma melacha lo chilakta bah, the same way
by מלאכה melacha there's no distinction, אף עינוי לא תחלוק בו. af
inui lo techalok bo.
By עינוי inui there's no distinction. What does it mean no distinction?
I thought it—what it—I would have thought it meant is that sometimes
it's about being in the sun, sometimes it's about being in the
cold. רש"י Rashi says no, there's no distinction about passive and active.
By מלאכה melacha you always refrain from מלאכה melacha by passively not
doing something. By עינוי, inui, sometimes I'm totally comfortable, so the only
way to do the עינוי inui is by being active. Sometimes I
could do it passively, but sometimes I'd have to do it actively,
and the juxtaposition to מלאכה melacha tells you only a type of
an עינוי inui that can always be done by being passive. Okay,
that's one thing we learn out. תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught
in another ברייתא. תענו את נפשותיכם, teanu et nafshoteichem, afflict yourself. יכול
ישב בחמה ובצינה ויצטער, yakhol yeshev bechama uvetzina veyitztaer, maybe I should
go sit in the sun or the cold. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar:
וכל מלאכה לא תעשו. vechol melacha lo taasu. מה מלאכה דבר שחייבין
עליו במקום אחר, ma melacha davar shechayavin alav bemakom acher, here's a
different דרשה, drasha, not about passive and active. The same way מלאכה
melacha that activity is a type of activity that other—that in other
places we know and as well as this place you get punished
for, right? Like if you do מלאכה melacha on שבת, Shabbat it's
a punishable offense. אף עינוי נפש שחייבין עליו במקום אחר. af inui
nefesh shechayavin alav bemakom acher. עינוי נפש inui nefesh has to be
something that if I did that activity in some other context it
would be punishable. Sitting in the, you know, so
sitting in an air-conditioned room is never an act that I would
be punishable for, as opposed to eating and drinking. I can find
you some eatings and drinkings that are punishable. What are they?
Forbidden foods. באיזה, be'eizeh, what type of an eating and drinking is—what
type of a thing is punishable elsewhere? זה פיגול ונותר. zeh pigul
venotar. First of all, like מלאכה melacha, we want to find something
that elsewhere you get כרת. So if you do מלאכה melacha on
שבת you get כרת, if you do a type of eating you
get כרת, if you eat פיגול ונותר, pigul venotar, could have said
חלב ודם. chelev vedam. אפילו פיגול ונותר שהן בכרת, afilu pigul venotar
shehen bekares, fine, that's where you
start, that those are—that's an act that otherwise. punishable. But לא אבי
הטבל שאינו בכרת, Lo avi hatevel she-eino b’kares, but that won't include
let's say טבל tevel which is very weighty but it's מיתה בידי
שמים, misa b’yedei shamayim, it's not כרת. Maybe that won't be prohibited.
תלמוד לומר תענו ועניתם את נפשתיכם, Talmud lomar te'anu vinisem es nafshoseichem,
the double language of תענו te'anu and ועניתם vinisem tells you a
much broader category. So it includes even טבל. tevel. ריבא, riba, it's
inclusive. Fine, אבי הטבל שבמיתה, Avi hatevel she-bu'misa, I'll include טבל tevel
which is a מיתה בידי שמים, misa b’yedei shamayim, heavenly death, ולא
אבי את הנבילה שאינה במיתה. v’lo avi es haneveila she-eina b’misa. Maybe
I won't include things that are simple negative prohibition: חזיר, chazer, נבילה.
neveila. תלמוד לומר תענו ועניתם את נפשתיכם, Talmud lomar te'anu vinisem es
nafshoseichem, ריבא. riba. No, it's very general, so once you've included one
type of forbidden foods, you're going to include all forbidden foods. אבי
את הנבילה שבלאו, Avi es haneveila she-bu’lav, I'll include forbidden foods, ולא
אבי את החולין שאינה בלאו. v’lo avi es hachulin she-eina b’lav. Fine,
I'll include forbidden foods, but maybe I won't be foresworn against, you
know, permissible foods, normal plain food. Maybe that I'll be allowed to
eat. תלמוד לומר תענו ועניתם את נפשתיכם, Talmud lomar te'anu vinisem es
nafshoseichem, ריבא. riba. No, it's very general, so once it's including forbidden
foods, it includes don't eat any food. אבי החולין שאינה בקום אכול.
Avi hachulin she-eina b’kumei achol. Fine, I'll include not eating types of
food that's a רשות, reshous, it's discretionary whether I eat, I don't
have an obligation to eat. ולא אבי את התרומה שהיא בקום אכול.
V’lo avi es hatruma she-hi b’kumei achol. Maybe I won't be prohibited
to eat תרומה truma where there's a מצוה mitzva to eat it.
תלמוד לומר תענו ועניתם את נפשתיכם, Talmud lomar te'anu vinisem es nafshoseichem,
ריבא. riba. No, we're including even foods that there's a מצוה mitzva
to eat. אבי את התרומה שאינה בבל תותירו. Avi es hatruma she-eina
b’bal sosiru. Fine, תרומה truma there's a מצוה mitzva to eat, but
there's not—let's sit back in a minute let's finish it—תרומה truma there's
a מצוה mitzva to eat, but if you don't eat it, you
haven't transgressed a prohibition of leaving it over. ולא אבי את הקדשים
שהם בבל תותירו. V’lo avi es hakodshim she-hem b’bal sosiru. קדשים kodshim
is a real מצוה mitzva to eat. You gotta eat it, if
you don't eat it within a day, you've transgressed. So maybe that
where there's a real mandate to eat, maybe that I'd be allowed
to eat on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur, תלמוד לומר תענו את נפשתיכם,
Talmud lomar ta'anu es nafshoseichem, ריבא. riba. It says תענו את נפשתיכם
ta'anu es nafshoseichem which is coming to include. So what have we
done here? What we basically have said is, how do I know
that תענו te'anu means don't eat? Because it—there are other types of
eating that are forbidden in the תורה. Torah. So if the תורה
Torah is forbidding something here and I don't know exactly what, I
look at the idea of מלאכה and I say it's got to
be forbidding something that in other contexts are forbidden and that has
to do with eating and drinking. Yes, it's true here, it's not
just eating and drinking forbidden foods, it's eating and drinking all foods,
but I know in other places the act of eating and drinking
is a forbidden act and therefore I'll say that's what the תורה
Torah is doing here. This by the way very much connects to
our previous discussion because here the whole basis of not eating and
drinking on יום כיפור is rooted in the world of מאכלות אסורות,
ma'achalos assuros, of forbidden foods. Yes, we broaden the category but conceptually
we say what does it mean don't eat? The same way elsewhere
the תורה Torah prohibits you from eating certain things. So yeah, on
יום כיפור, the certain things is everything. Fine, but it's a type
of a מאכלות אסורות ma'achalos assuros in a very broad way. Very
unusual way of thinking about it but that's what you have here,
thinking about it as מאכלות אסורות. ma'achalos assuros. As opposed to the
previous one by the way, which linked not eating to the idea
of מלאכה and linked it to being passive and not engaging, that
is very suggestive of רמב"ם's Rambam approach which is it's a type
of שבות, shvus, right? Refrain, refrain from מלאכה, refrain from eating and
drinking. It's a type of just passive stepping back. So two very
different conceptual models of what—where we learn the prohibition and how to
sort of see where it's located. Now the גמרא says, the ברייתא
continues and if you want, you didn't like that explanation, הרי אומר,
harei omer, base it on the following way: והאבדתי את הנפש ההיא,
V'ha'avadeti es hanefesh hahi, that if you—anybody who doesn't—who doesn't afflict themselves
I will destroy that soul. עינוי, inui, so that tells us what
type of עינוי inui we're talking about. עינוי שהוא אבדת הנפש. Inui
she'hu avedas hanefesh. It's not just the punishment,
it's signaling to us what type of עינוי inui we're referring to.
An עינוי inui that leads to a wasting away of the—not soul
but of the body. ואיזה, V'eizeh, what type of—of an affliction will
actually lead to losing of some of your body? You know, you
drop some calories. זה אכילה ושתיה. Zeh achila v'shtiya. That's eating and
drinking, which by the way is the third conceptual model of עינוי.
inui. It's the actual sense of hurting yourself. Right, so we have
three great models for it. It's a type of מאכלות אסורות ma'achalos
assuros which is broadened to include everything. It's a type of stepping
back from the world like מלאכה and it's a type of איבוד
הנפש, ibbud hanefesh, actually taking—you know, hurting yourself, taking something away from
your body. מאי ואינפשך לומר? Mai v'inapshcha lomar? Why do we have
to look for another פסוק? pasuk? What was the matter of basing
it on the idea of forbidden eating and drinking? וכי תימא בעריות
קמשתעי קרא? V'chi teima b’arayos kameshtai kara? No, I'll give you another
type of activity that is elsewhere forbidden other than eating and drinking.
עריות, arayos, sex. Sex is forbidden in certain contexts, right, with adultery,
you know, relatives and so on. So maybe that's what's being prohibited?
Don't have any sex even a husband and wife. Okay, the same
way you're saying don't have any eating. הרי אומר והאבדתי את הנפש,
Harei omer v'ha'avadeti es hanefesh, עינוי שיש בו אבדת הנפש, inui sheyesh
bo avedas hanefesh, ואיזה זה אכילה ושתיה. v'eizeh zeh achila v'shtiya. Okay,
so that's why we have these three different sources. By the way,
I should point out that a number of מפרשי המקרא mefarshei ha-mikra
want to argue that it's basically implicit in the word נפש nefesh
that
נפש nefesh in biblical Hebrew, and you certainly find it in תנ"ך,
Tanakh, as you know like in משלי Mishlei and whatever, can refer
to the throat. Okay, and in Semitic cognates the word נפש nefesh
refers to the throat or the appetite. So תענו את נפשותיכם, te-anu
et nafshoteichem, some want to suggest means afflict your appetite, your throat,
and that נפש nefesh very much suggests the world of eating and
drinking.
אכילה ושתיה achilah u-shtiah always refers to the throat?
Not, yeah, not always, but it could mean. Okay, let's just read
one more thing. דבי ר' ישמעאל תנא: de-vei Rabbi Yishmael tana: נאמר
כאן עינוי ne-emar kan inui ונאמר להלן עינוי. ve-ne-emar le-hallan inui. מה
להלן עינוי רעבון, mah le-hallan inui re-avon, the same way an עינוי
inui we'll find later means sort of starving, אף כאן עינוי רעבון.
af kan inui re-avon. Here too it's starving. What עינוי inui is
about starving? Where it says God gave you the man,
ויענך וירעיבך. va-ye-anecha va-yar-ivecha. Okay, he afflicted you and he made you
go hungry. So there you see exactly a juxtaposition of affliction and
going hungry. Okay, so we will pick up with this other, this
new approach tomorrow. יישר כח.
yasher koach.